Some of the things I'm going to share with you, I want you to remember for a long, long time,
我会分享一些事情 我想让你们想起一段长时间
because the ideas I want to translate for you drastically affected my life.
因为我想把我的想法传递给你们 这对我的生活严重影响了
So the man who shared with me ideas that changed my life, I want to share with you three of those
所以我分享的男人 想要改变我的生活 我想分享三个基本的主题
basic subjects. When I met him, I was 25 years old, and when I first got acquainted with him,
我想分享三个基本的主题 当我见到他的时候 我年纪是25岁 当我第一次认识他
I used a lot of excuses as to why I wasn't doing well. And he said, well, tell me a little bit
我用了很多的道理 为何我做得不好 他問我 你故事的故事
about your story. And I told him, you know, I was behind on my bills, had pennies in my pocket,
我告诉他 我告诉他 我背后的钱 钱包包包
nothing in the bank, that I was embarrassed about being behind on my big mouth promises to my family.
钱包包包 但我害怕 我背后的大口证明 我跟家人说 我背后的大口证明 我跟家人说
And then he gave me one little simple phrase that really forever changed my life. And here's what
然后他给我一句 非常简单的说话 让我的生活永远改变 他说
he said, Mr. Rohn, if you want the future to change for you, you've got to change. And he said,
如果你想将来改变 你必須改变 如果不改变 你将来的六年
if you don't change, the next six years of your life is going to be just like the last six.
将会像过去的六年 你还会背后的钱
You'll still be behind on your bills. You'll still be behind on your promises.
你还会背后的大口证明 你还会背后的大口证明 但他给我一句
But then he gave it to me in the form of a promise. When I was 25 years old, I've remembered it all
但他给我一句 大口证明 当我年纪25岁 我记得了所有的年代
these years, and I've shared this promise now with probably over three million people in the last 30
我记得了所有的年代 我现在分享的大口证明 有可能是近三百万人 在过去的三十多年
plus years. And it's going to be valid for you. So listen carefully to this promise. My teacher said
这会是对你的 所以要听清楚大口证明 我的老师说 年輕人
to me, young man, if you will change, everything will change for you. If you will get better,
如果你会改变 所有事情都会改变 如果你会改变 你会改变
everything will get better for you. What a clear message that was for me. He said, if you'll change
所有事情都会改变 这给我一句很清楚的说法 他说 如果你想改变你的思想
your philosophy, if you'll change your habits, if you'll refine your thinking, if you'll change
如果你想改变你的习慣 如果你想改善你的思想 如果你想改变
and accept some new disciplines, if you'll turn the corner where you've been in the past, go for
並接受新的规矩 如果你想转变 在过去的你
a new life for the future. He said, all kinds of remarkable things will happen for you. If you will
去找新的生活 他说 所有的奇妙的事情 都会改变你 如果你会改变
change. Before I met Mr. Shouf, I used to cross my fingers and say, I sure hope things will change.
如果你会改变 我以前见过Mr. Shouf 我经常用手指来说 我希望事情会改变 我希望政府会改变
I was hoping the government would change and the tax structure would change and that my boss would
我希望政府会改变 法律会改变 我老闆会改变
change and pay me more money. I was hoping that, you know, economics would change and prices would
我会賺更多钱 我希望经济会改变 價格会降低
come down. And I was hoping that circumstances would get better. And then I discovered from my
我希望情況会改善 我从我的老师发现 这些事情会繼續一样
teacher that those things are going to continue the same. In fact, all of those things that happen
这些事情会繼續一样 事實上 所有事情都像风吹过
to us is kind of like the wind that blows and the wind blows on us all. But if you just let the wind
所有事情都像风吹过 风吹过我们所有人 但如果只让风吹过 我告诉你
blow, I'm telling you, it won't take you where you want to go. All of us must use this wind to take
你不可以去哪里你想去 我们所有人都必須用这风吹 帶我们去夢想
us to the dreams we've got, to the equities we want, to the money we want, to the income we want
帶我们去夢想 去想要的财富 想要的钱 想要的薪水 想要的所有东西
and to all the things we want our life to have. This is where we want to go and we've got a good
我们想要的生活 我们想要的地方 我们想去的地方 我们有了好风
wind, but we must not leave our future just to the wind, just to the economy, just to the structure
但我们必須不离开 我们的未来 只为风吹 只为经济 只为今天事情的構成
of the way things are happening today. Here's what we must learn to do. And that is set a good sail.
只为今天事情的構成 我们必須学习 设置好风浪
And if you'll learn to set a good sail, and that's what my teacher taught me in those early days,
如果我们能设置好风浪 我老师教我 在那些早期教我 他教我
he said, Mr. Rohn, the wind is going to blow however it's going to blow.
风吹过的风是会吹的 但风吹过的风是会吹的
Politics are going to be politics and the economy is going to be the economy.
政治是会是政治 经济是会是经济 但無论如何
And however it turns out, that's the way it's going to be. What you must learn to do is not to wish
风吹过的风是会是 你必須学习的 不是想要好风
for a better wind. That's naive. The key is to wish for the wisdom and the skills and the learning
这是很难的 这是很难的 最重要的是 学习才能设置好风浪
so that you can set a better sail. And so that's what I did at age 25. I went to work not on the
学习才能设置好风浪 所以我年齡25岁 我沒有去工作经济
economy. I went to work not on the community. I didn't go to work to try to change the government.
我沒有去工作经济 我沒有去工作社会 我沒有去工作改变政府
I didn't go to work to try to change my boss or the company. I didn't go to work to try to
我沒有去工作改变老闆或公司 我沒有去工作改变情況
change circumstances. I went to work to try to change myself. And I picked up that promise
我沒有去工作改变自己 我把那份承诺都承诺了 我老师教我
my teacher shared with me, that if I would change, my income would change. If I would change,
我老师教我 如果我改变 我的薪金会改变 如果我改变
my bank account would change. If I would change, my future would change. And sure enough, his promise
我的銀行会改变 如果我改变 我的未来会改变 确實地 他承诺是对的
came true for me. The first six years of my economic life, I wound up broke. Those pennies
他承诺是对的 我在我经济上的第一六年 我被毁了 我的钱包沒了
in my pocket, nothing in the bank, behind on my promises. The second six years of my economic life,
銀行沒有了 我承诺的背后 在我经济上的第二六年 我被豪宅了
I wound up rich. But interestingly enough, the second six years of my economic life,
我被豪宅了 但有趣的是 在我经济上的第二六年
the government was about the same and the economy was about the same. You know, the companies were
我 Filladores顧問 onions shower 吃買吧 这时候,沒有人可以知道
about the same. What they paid was the same. Circumstances around me were the same. You know,
学生经济之大
my negative relatives were the same. But I was not the same. That's how my life changed. That's how
방송延續 Judah
things started working for me, changing my life all those years ago. So that's what I wanted to
小 consisting 得了深eding 得说 W议会
share with you to begin with. This beginning of what Mr. Shove shared with me, that if I wanted
W议会 周先生 他跟我说如果我想改变我的生活
my life to change, this was what I was going to have to do. And so he broke it down into three
他跟我说如果我想改变我的生活 这就是我必須做的事 所以他将它分成三个主题
subjects that really made an impact on my life. And I want to share those with you.
所以他将它分成三个主题 让我的生活有影响 我想和你们分享
The first subject he called personal development.
第一个主题是 个人发展
And the second subject he called setting goals. And the third was how to become financially
第二点是设计目标 第三点是如何成为 金融自由
independent. And I'd like to give you just a few clues from those three major subjects that so
金融自由 我将给你们一些主题 关於这三个主题
dramatically affected my life. And let's get started. The first one is personal development.
让我的生活有影响 我们开始吧 第一个主题是个人发展
Now in illustrating personal development, Mr. Shove, my teacher, started with
在画面上 我的教授,蕭勒先生 开始学金融
money. You know, money's not the only place to start in talking personal development. But it's
开始学金融 金融並非是个人发展的主题 但这是他开始的
where he started. So let me share the thoughts he shared with me back then. Let me share them with
让我分享他当时的想法 和你们分享
you. Here's the best lesson I can give you on economics. It's very simple. We get paid for
和你们分享 我可以给你们一个最好的教授 在经济上 非常简单 我们被賣给了
bringing value to the marketplace. That's about as simple as I can put economics. We get paid for
我们被賣给了 在市場上的價值 我可以把经济放在这里 我们被賣给了
bringing value to the marketplace. Now it takes time to bring value to the marketplace. However,
我们被賣给了 在市場上的價值 现在,我们要賣给市場上的價值 但是
we do not get paid for time. So we cross that out. Mistakenly, the man says, I'm making about
我们沒有时间賣给市場上的價值 所以我们要把这个交给市場上的價值 錯误地说 我賣了20个小时
$20 for an hour. Not true. If that was true, you could just stay home, right? Have them send your
我賣了20个小时 这不可能 如果是真的 你可以在家里待著
money. So that's not true. We don't get paid for time. We get paid for value brought to the
让他们送你钱 这不可能 我们沒有时间賣给市場上的價值 我们賣给市場上的價值
marketplace. Now, since that's true, here's one of the key questions of my talk to you today.
帶给市場上的價值 既然是真的 今天我会問你一个重要的問题
Is it possible to become twice as valuable to the marketplace and make twice as much money
是否可能能够成为市場上的價值 和同时賺到兩倍钱
in the same time? Is that possible? The answer is yes. Could you become three times as valuable
是否可能 答案是是 你能否成为市場上的價值三倍
as you might be right now to the marketplace and make three times as much money in the same time?
就像你现在的情況 去市場上賺到三倍钱 同时賺到兩倍钱
And the answer is yes. Five times? Ten times? Of course. Now there's some key questions to ask here.
答案是是 五倍?十倍? 当然 现在我们要問的問题很重要
Why would the marketplace pay someone only $5 an hour? Very simple answer. They're not very
为何市場上能賣给市場上的價值 只賣五个小时 简单的答案 市場上的價值不算很重要
valuable to the marketplace. Now we must underline to the marketplace. This person might be a very
市場上的價值不算很重要 我们必須要说明市場上的價值 这个人可能是一个很重要的兄弟
valuable brother. Yes. Member of the family. Valuable. Yes. Valuable member of the church.
这个人可能是一个很重要的兄弟 是的 家族的重要人物 是的 教会的重要人物
Of course. Valuable citizen of the country. Yes. Valuable in the sight of God. No doubt. We're all
当然 国家的重要民主人物 是的 在神的眼中的重要人物 不可能 我们在神的眼中的價值都不一样
of equal value in the sight of God. But if you're not very valuable to the marketplace,
我们在神的眼中的價值都不一样 但如果市場上的價值不算很重要
you don't get much money. You say, well, it shouldn't be that way. Well, then you got to
你不会賺到很多钱 你会说 这不应该这样 那你必須要开始自己的国家
start your own country. You know, this one's been in process for 200 years and this is the best we've
那你必須要开始自己的国家 这个国家已经在200年来的过程中 这就是我们目前能够成功的最好的
been able to come up with so far. But here's the key. You don't have to stay here. But here's what
这就是我们目前能够成功的最好的 但这就是关鍵 你不必留在这里 但这是他告诉我的
he said to me. In climbing this ladder economically, all you have to do is work harder on yourself
但这是他告诉我的 在经济上爬上这条路 你只要努力 在自己身上
than you do on your job. Once I heard that, it made sense to me. I kept hoping that everything
而不是在工作上 我听到这句话 就很合理了 我一直希望 所有事情都会改变
else would change around me. Found out that if I went to work on myself, worked on my skills,
所有事情都会改变 我发现 如果我自己去工作 我用我的技术
worked on my language, if I became better than I was each year, if I grew in skills and language
我用我的语言 如果每年我成长得更好 如果我成长的技术、语言、语言
and vocabulary and competence, then I would become attractive to the marketplace. Not very
如果我成长的技术、语言、语言 和技术 那么我会成为市場上的吸引力 不久前
long ago, a company called me and said, Mr. Owen, we're expanding internationally. We'd like to have
不久前 有一个公司叫我 说 我们在国际上的开发 我们想要你帮助我们
a bit of your expertise to help us. Would you give us a bit of your time? We'll add some millions to
我们想要你帮助我们 你给我们一点时间 我们会给你一百万的钱
your fortune. And I said, okay. And I thought later, isn't that interesting? They would call me. Then
我答应他们 好 后来我心想 他们会叫我 我第二次想
my second thought was, of course they'd call me. Who else would they call? I can get the job done.
当然他们会叫我 誰会叫我 我可以做到
Now, what a contrast for me. Farm boy from Idaho raised in obscurity. Parents of modest means broke
现在我看到了 我从 Idaho 一个農民 长大了一个隐藏的家庭 但是我年輕的时候
when I was 25. How come I would get a telephone call and someone offer me a lot of money to help
被我年齡大了 我应该怎么会得到电话的电话號码 让別人提供我 很多的钱 来帮助他们
them in expanding around the world? Simple answer. Evidently, something happened to me between age 25
让世界的开发 简单的答案 我心想 现在我年齡大了 我应该怎么做 会有什么事情发生
and where I am today. And I can tell you where it all started from my teacher, Mr. Schof, who said to
我能告诉你 从我的老师 老师说 我们不必去改变
me, we don't have to change what's going on out there. That's the wind that's blowing.
现在的事情 我们不必去改变 现在的事情 只要我们改变 现在的事情
All we have to do is change what's going on in here. And now there's several ways to do that
我们不必去改变 我们不必去改变 现在的事情 在这里发生 现在我们可以做到
on personal development. And let me give you those ways. Here's the first one. We must learn from
在个人发展上 让我给你们一些方法 首先 我们必須从个人经验来学会
personal experience. Pretty simple. Learn from what happens to you. Take a look back over the
我们必須从个人经验来学会 简单的 学会了什么 在过去幾个月 你做了一些錯误吗
last few months. Did you make some mistakes? How could you correct those for the future?
你做了一些錯误吗 你能否改变这件事 在过去幾个月
Take a look back over the last year. Have you done it right or done it wrong?
你能否改变这件事 你能否改变这件事 你能否改变这件事
Let's correct it for the next year. Learn from your personal experience. Mr. Schof asked me when
让我们将来改变 学会了什么 从个人经验来学会 我第一次见到蕭峰
I first met him, he said, Mr. Rohn, how are you doing? You've been out there now six years. And
我第一次见到蕭峰 蕭峰说 怎么你? 我問蕭峰 你已经在这幾年
I said, I'm not doing very well. He said, I suggest you not do that anymore. What a simple,
我想你还是会改变 蕭峰说 我建议你別再做那些事情 我的情況
swift analysis to my situation. He said, if you keep doing it, the next six years will be like the
我的情況 很简单的分析 他提出 如果你繼續做 将来的这六年
last six. You don't want that to happen. Let's make the changes. So learn from your personal
就像最后的那六年 你不能再做了 让我们改变 从个人经验来学会
experience. Now here's number two why I came to share this video experience with you today.
从个人经验来学会 这是2號 今天和你们分享这段影片的经历
And that I call it OPE, other people's experiences. That's me, other people. That's your teacher,
我称之为OPE,其他人的经历 那是我,其他人 那是你的老师,其他人
other people. That's your friends and colleagues, other people. The people you meet that can pass
那是你的老师,其他人 那是你的朋友、同学,其他人 你遇到的人,他们的经历可以跟著你
along to you their experiences, what's happened to them, the mistakes they made, how they corrected
你遇到的人,他们的经历可以跟著你 他们做的錯误,他们的改变
them, how they changed their health and changed their bank account and changed their income and
他们的健康,他们的銀行,他们的薪水 他们的未来,这些就是其他人
changed their future. That's it. Other people. Now there's two kinds of people to learn from.
他们的未来,这些就是其他人 现在有兩种人可以学到的 第一种是失敗
One is failures. It's two bad failures. Don't give seminars, right? That would be valuable.
第一种是失敗 失敗太差了,不要给他们学习,对吗? 这会是很重要的
Bring your notebook, have them tell you how they lost it all and threw it all away,
拿你的记忆记,让他们告诉你 他们失敗了,把所有东西都丟掉 把他们的健康丟掉,把他们的朋友丟掉
threw their health away and threw their friendships away and things didn't work out well.
把他们的健康丟掉,把他们的朋友丟掉 如果事情沒有成功,这会是很重要的
That would be valuable. But now then we must also learn from positive people that have done well.
如果事情沒有成功,这会是很重要的 现在我们也要从正面学习 那些已经做得好,他们的健康
They've got the health and so we ask them, how did you become so healthy? They've got the skills,
那些已经做得好,他们的健康 他们的健康,我们問他们 他们的技巧,我们問他们
so we ask them, how did you become this skillful? They've got the income, so we ask them, how did
他们的技巧,我们問他们 他们的薪水,我们問他们 他们在短时间內,如何才能到这里
you get here in such a short period of time? So now here's what's important in personal development.
他们在短时间內,如何才能到这里 现在,这是个人发展的重要点
In learning from other people, we learn number one by observation.
在学习其他人,我们第一,学习观察
We learn what we see. We watch people that are successful in what they do.
我们学习我们看到的,我们看著人们成功 在运动上,我们看著他们的技术
In sports, we watch their disciplines. In business, we watch their disciplines
在运动上,我们看著他们的技术 在观察中,我们看到的,我们看到的
by observation. What we can see. The reason I created this video is something that you could
我創作这个影片是为了让你能看到 一些人的经历,被你传递给你
see someone's experiences translated for you. Second, we learn by what we hear.
第二,我们学习我们听到的 我有一些我的课程,用卡片
I've got some of my lectures on cassette tapes, so you know you can take them with you wherever you
我有一些我的课程,用卡片 让你可以拿到,你去哪里都可以
go and learn by listening. Turn your car into a mobile classroom and listen. And then listen to
学习听,把你的车载到电子学校 然后听 然后我们就开始学习 然后听
the sermon on Sunday morning. Listen to the lectures. Listen to the teacher. Listen to
然后听 然后在星期天学会上听课
someone who's got something good to say. And then number three is vitally important on personal
听教授,听到有什么好说的 第三,在个人发展上,非常重要
development, and that is read all the books. All the books you can possibly read in your lifetime.
第三,在个人发展上,非常重要 就是,可以在你的生命中,可以读书
Mr. Shouf got me started on my library. I've got one of the better libraries. Haven't read
就是,可以在你的生命中,可以读书 我开始学习我的书本 我有一间比較好的书本
everything in it, but I feel smarter just walking in it, my library. At least I was smart enough to
我有一间比較好的书本 我沒有全部都读过,但我感觉比較聰明 在书本里走著走著
buy it. Now I've got to be smart enough to read it. Then of course I've got to be smart enough to
在书本里走著走著 至少我買得很聰明 现在我读得很聰明
decide what's valuable and then do it. But this one is very important. Become a good reader.
然后我決定要做得很聰明 然后做 但这本书很重要,成为好读者
Some books that helped change my life. Mr. Shouf recommended, of course, the Bible.
但这本书很重要,成为好读者 一些书,帮助我的生活
And my parents made sure I was a pretty good scholar by the time I was 18. That's been so
我老师推薦的,当然是《教会》 我父母确保我当时是一个很好的学生
beneficial for me, drawing from those illustrations, reading about those stories, people who made it,
我父母确保我当时是一个很好的学生 这对我来说,很有利 从那些图片中写出来
and people who didn't make it, and what the difference was. And then other books that
从那些图片中写出来 那些故事的读书 那些人做的,那些人沒有的 那些人做的,那些人沒有的
helped to really change my life. One called Think and Grow Rich by Napoleon Hill. And then a book
那些人做的,那些人沒有的 然后还有其他书 帮助我的生活 一本叫《想和成长富有》
that helped me become financially independent by the time I was 31. And that book is called
写来的,是由Napoleon Hill写的 然后还有一本书 帮助我当时31岁时
The Richest Man in Babylon by George Clason. But I started reading the books, attending the classes,
帮助我当时31岁时 成为金融独立的书 那本书叫《富有男人在巴布拉倫》
making sure that I got in front of people that had something good to say. And then I started
我开始读书,去探訪课堂 确保我面对有些人
keeping a journal. One of the major things my teacher taught me was to keep a journal.
有什么好说的 然后我开始保留了一本书
He said, don't trust your memory. If you hear something good, don't trust your memory.
我老师教我保留一本书的一大部分 他说,不要相信记忆
If you hear something good, just make a little note and write it down.
如果听到有什么好说的 就写一本小书,然后把它写下来
Now at first I took notes on pieces of paper and torn off corners and backs of old envelopes.
当时我先写了一本书 然后把图片撕掉 然后把图片放在舊的袋子里
And it didn't serve me well, you know, thrown in a drawer. Then I learned to keep a journal,
但我做得不好 就放进了一張桌子里 然后我学会保留了一本书
a bound copy of all my notes. So I would suggest you do the same. Things that impress you, a poem
一本全是我的书 所以我建议你做一样的 有什么让你感到印象 有什么书让你感到印象
that impresses you. When you attend a class, some of the ideas that impressed you, jot them down.
有什么书让你感到印象 当你去探訪课堂 有什么印象让你感到印象 把它撕掉
If you read something in a magazine, right, some ideas, take those out, put them in your journal.
你读了一本书 有什么想法 把它撕掉,放进你的记忆盒里
Keep a good journal. The rest of your life, this will serve you well. My journals make up a
保留一本好记忆盒 你的生命中 这会帮你好用 我的记忆盒 会做出一大部分
significant portion of my own library. And if you saw my library and saw my journals, I tell you
会做出一大部分 我的自己的书本 如果你看到我的书本 或者看见我的记忆盒
what you'd have to say. This is the library and these are the journals of a very serious student.
我告诉你 这是我的书本 这是一个非常严格的学生的记忆盒
No wonder Mr. Rohn is invited to lecture and speak on his experiences around the world.
沒想到,Mr. Rohn 邀請了你来授课 並分享他在世界上的经验
So I want the same thing to happen to you. Value captured that you can resort to later.
所以我想你做一样的事 你能够从后再回头 去体验到你
Go back over it and review it and let it become valuable to you. Work harder on yourself than you
再去考慮到 让它变得对你有價值 你比工作更加辛苦
do on your job. Develop the skills. Learn the lessons. Take the classes. Absorb all that is
你比工作更加辛苦 发展技巧 学习习慣 学习教授 让你今天所教的东西 都吸收了
being taught to you these days. And then later on, of course, you can sort it out. What's valuable
都吸收了 然后之后你能够 把这些东西都分开
to you and how to refine it for your business and for your life and for your future. But the main
让你能够 改善自己的生命 和未来 但最重要的是
thing is to get it and start this process of personal change, personal development.
让你能够 开始这段 个人改变 个人发展 让我再说一次
And let me say it one more time. If you will change, everything will change for you. You'll
让我再说一次 如果你会改变 所有事情都会改变 你永远都不会变成一样
never be the same. You'll keep growing as you look back on a few months, look back on a few years.
你会繼續发展 当你再回头 再回头幾个月 再回头幾个年
You won't believe the progress you can make economically, your relationship with your family,
你不会相信 你能够进一步 在经济上 你的关系 和你的家人
your friends, and whether you're in sports or economics or whatever. I'm telling you
和你的朋友 不管你进行运动 经济学或其他东西
that whole process of committing yourself for personal change,
整个改变自己的 个人改变 个人價值
personal value can really make your life unique and worthwhile.
都能让你的生命 更加独特和值得